Don Yoder collection of tape and disc recordings
American Folklife Center, Library of Congress
Don Yoder collection of tape and disc recordings 1951-2005
AFC 2003/051
Yoder, Don
381 items
1 box (approximately 79 items)
77 sound tape reels: analog; 10 in.
92 sound tape reels: analog; various sizes
128 sound cassettes: analog
1 sound disc: analog, 45 rpm; 6 in.
2 photographic prints: black and white; 3 1/2 in. x 5 in.
1 photographic negative: black and white; 3 in. x 1 1/2 in.
1 videocassette (VHS): sound; 1/2 in.
American Folklife Center, Library of Congress Washington, D.C.
Collection of field recordings made by professor Don Yoder to document various religious sects and religious and secular folk traditions primarily in Pennsylvania and in the northeastern United States. Included are recordings of Pennsylvania German conversation, interviews, hymns, prayers, church services including sermons, folk dance music, humorous songs, and folk festivals. Manuscripts include a few published articles by Don Yoder and various folk festival programs.
Provenance
Don Yoder, donation; 2003, 2016.
Accruals
No further accruals expected.
Related Materials
Alan Lomax Ohio and Indiana collection (AFC 1938/004)
Marcus Bach "Preserving Iowa's Religious Heritage" collection, part 1 (AFC 1943/013)
Don Yoder collection of wire recordings (AFC 1970/004)
Marian P. Michael collection of Texas Baptist hymns and services (AFC 1980/033)
Symposium on Rural Hymnody Collection, Berea College Special Collections and Archives, Berea, Kentucky. (RG 11.02)
Don Yoder papers #4244, Southern Historical Collection, The Wilson Library, University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill
Access and Restrictions
The collection is open for research. To request materials, please contact the Folklife Reading Room at https://hdl.loc.gov/loc.afc/folklife.contact
Certain restrictions to use or copying of materials may apply.
Biographical Notes
Born in 1921, in Altoona, Pennsylvania, Don Yoder grew up immersed in the traditions of Pennsylvania German culture. Educated at Franklin and Marshall College (A.B., 1942 and B.D., 1945), and at the University of Chicago (Ph.D., 1947), Yoder taught at Franklin and Marshall College (1949-1956), and then at the University of Pennsylvania (1956-1996), where he also was chair of the Department of Folklore and Folklife from 1966-1969. He retired from teaching in 1996. He authored and co-authored hundreds of publications, traveled and lectured widely, and held varied posts, including director of the Pennsylvania Folklife Society (which he co-founded), editor of Pennsylvania Folklife, president of the American Folklore Society, and Professor Emeritus of Folklife Studies, University of Pennsylvania. He was a member of Phi Beta Kappa, and was elected fellow to the American Antiquarian Society and the American Genealogical Society, among others. He introduced the European concept and practice of folklife studies in the United States. He died in 2015.
Scope and Content
Collection of field recordings made by professor Don Yoder to document various religious sects and religious and secular folk traditions primarily in Pennsylvania and in the northeastern United States. Included are recordings of Pennsylvania German conversation, interviews, hymns, prayers, church services including sermons, folk dance music, humorous songs, and folk festivals. Some tapes document Don Yoder's lectures and contain materials prepared for his classes on folk religion recorded by Dr. Yoder and other scholars and by his students at the University of Pennsylvania. Recordings were made of various events including the first Pennsylvania Dutch Harvest Frolic, August 30-September 1, 1961; and the second annual and other years of the Pennsylvania Dutch Folk Festival, Kutztown, Pennsylvania. (recorded from a broadcast by WEEU) where participants were interviewed about local history; folk religious beliefs and practices, including prayer and the himmelsbrief; and healing traditions including Pennsylvania Dutch powwowing, and religious healing in Catholic and other traditions. Local choirs performed Pennsylvania German hymns and revival hymns, some in English; and Christmas music from Pennsylvania Dutch country. Other interviewees are a Russian woman who emigrated as a child and who speaks about Jewish customs related to pregnancy and birth; Italian Americans interviewed about miracles of healing, intercessory prayer, and the St. Anthony Beneficial Society, Glassboro, N.J.; Baptist church singers from Kentucky demonstrating lining-out hymnody; interviews about Shakers; and other unidentified content. Included is a sound tape reel of Korean shamanic chant. Manuscripts include a few published articles by Don Yoder and varied folk festival programs.
Arrangement
Organized by format into the following series:
Series 1: Manuscripts
Series 2: Sound Recordings
Series 3: Graphic Materials
Series 4: Moving Images
Selected Search Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the LC Catalog. They are grouped by name of person or organization, by subject or location, and by occupation and listed alphabetically.
People
Anderson, Cheryl P.; Bailer, Sophia, 1870-1954; Bechtel, Ernest Waldo; Brendel, John B., 1911-1971; Brightbill, Alvin F. (Alvin Franz); Craigie, Carter Walker; Cronister, Henry, 1881-1976; Dreamdigger, Ruth, 1919-1997; Eberley, Sophia E., 1896-1966; Eckert, Frank, 1870-1959; Fry, Dorathy V. Eberly, 1914-2012; Gable, Valeria, 1866-1955; Green, Rose Basile, 1914-2003; Hertzog, Phares H., 1880-1988; Hostetler, John A. (John Andrew), 1918-2001; Lapp, John E., 1905-1988; Mealing, Francis Mark, 1938-; Michael, Marian P., 1927-2011; Ossman, Agnes M., 1870-1960; Paul, Mary, 1859-1951; Peachey, Samuel H. (Samuel Hildebertus), 1892-1973; Raichelson, Richard M., 1941-; Seldomridge, Amos Leon, 1920-2016; Snyder, Mabel L., 1902-1973; Summerton, Larry; Thomas, Mary Larkin, 1886-1981; Trein, Jennie C., 1879-1977; Watson, Ora, 1908-2004; Weaver, Carrie Bonser; Weaver, William Woys, 1947-; Womack, Daniel, 1904-1996; Wright, Daniel, 1918-2001; Wright, Lois W., 1921-1998; Wright-Summerton, Rachel; Yoder, Don; Yoder, Emma L., 1873-1961
Organizations
Ephrata Cloister; International Communal Studies Association.; Pennsylvania Dutch Folk Festival: (2nd: 1951: Kutztown, Pa.); Pennsylvania Dutch Harvest Frolic: (1st: 1961: Lancaster, Pa.); WEEU (Radio station: Reading, Pa.)
Subjects
African Americans--Social life and customs.; Baptists--Kentucky--Hymns.; Christmas music--Pennsylvania.; Field recordings--New Jersey.; Field recordings--Pennsylvania.; Folk dance music--Pennsylvania.; Folk festivals--Pennsylvania.; Folk music--Pennsylvania.; Folk songs, Pennsylvania German--Pennsylvania.; Healing--Religious aspects.; Hymns, English--Pennsylvania.; Hymns, German--Pennsylvania.; Hymns, Pennsylvania German--Pennsylvania.; Hymns, Pennsylvania German.; Italian American Catholics--New Jersey--Religion.; Italian American Catholics--New Jersey--Social life and customs.; Jews, Russian--United States--Social life and customs.; Pennsylvania Dutch--Pennsylvania--Music.; Pennsylvania Dutch--Pennsylvania--Religion.; Pennsylvania Dutch--Pennsylvania--Social life and customs.; Powwows (healers); Quakers--Genealogy.; Revival hymns--Pennsylvania.; Shakers--Religion.; Society of Friends.; Syrian Americans--Social life and customs.
Places
Padanaram Settlement (Ind.)
Form/Genre
Field recordings.; Interviews.; Lectures.; Prayers.; Radio programs.
Container List
- Series 1: Manuscripts
  - Original manuscript materials from the sound recording containers, One linear inch. (Box-folder 1/1)
    Includes letters, documentation about the contents, specific sound recordings, and related materials.
  - Behney, William H. Choruses adapted to standard hymns: a collection for revival services, prayer meetings, etc. Lebanon Courier Print, ca. 1890s., 1 item: 107 pages. (Box-folder 1/2)
    66 hymns, each indexed by first line.
  - Publications by or about Don Yoder (Box-folder 1/3)
    1968 Festival of American Folklife, The Smithsonian Museum (program). Includes a one-page essay by Yoder on folklore and folklife.
    Pennsylvania Folklife (Vol. XXVII, No. 4; Summer 1978). Includes an essay by Yoder on "The Dialect Church Service in Pennsylvania German Culture."
    Pennsylvania Heritage (Vol. XXXII, No. 2; Spring 2006). Includes an essay on Yoder's life and work.
  - Original tape boxes for sound recordings, 9 boxes. (Box 1)
    A selection of nine original boxes from sound tape reels.
- Series 2: Sound Recordings
  Recorded circa 1951-1979. Genres include spirituals, powwowing, dance music, and other styles. Sound quality varies, especially since the majority of recordings were made outdoors. Also includes one sound tape reel of Korean shamanic chant. Recordings were not received in any particular order, so the materials have been organized by topic or event, when known. SR066 (a 10-inch sound tape reel) was found to be blank. Unless otherwise noted, details about the recordings are sourced from accompanying documentation. During digitization SR001 through SR076 were wound from the original reels onto 10-inch reels, during a brief time when this was standard practice for long-term storage of sound reels at the Library of Congress.
  - Sound recording, July 2 (year unidentified), RAA 46835; 1 sound tape reel (00:19:45): analog, 7 1/2 ips, full track, mono, 7 in. (Item-id AFC 2003/051: SR001)
    Recorded at the Pennsylvania Dutch Folk Festival, Kutztown, Pennsylvania. Participants include two men who, in turn, speak in Pennsylvania German and in English. Mabel Snyder speaks in Pennsylvania German and in English.
  - Sound recording, September 6, 1958, RAA 46836; 1 sound tape reel (00:31:23): analog, 7 1/2 ips, half track, mono; 7 in. (Item-id AFC 2003/051: SR002)
    Frank Eckert tells stories.
  - Sound recording, undated, RAA 46837; 1 sound tape reel: analog, 7 1/2 ips, half track, mono; 7 in. (Item-id AFC 2003/051: SR003)
    Possibly recorded in Lancaster, Pennsylvania.
    Side A
    Dance music (heavy footfalls indicate dancing), performed by an unidentified group, with fiddler and callers.
    Side B
    Dance music (heavy footfalls indicate dancing), performed by an unidentified group, with fiddler and callers, and an unidentified group sings "Oh Susannah."
  - Sound recording, September 1, 1961, RAA 46838; 1 sound tape reel (00:28:11): analog, 7 1/2 ips, half track, mono; 7 in. (Item-id AFC 2003/051: SR004)
    1st Pennsylvania Dutch Harvest Frolic. The first six selections are folk songs or spoken-word segments. The balance are hymns and/or prayers, performed by Mabel Snyder. Announcer (Don Yoder?) introduces performers and songs.
    00:00:07 Don Yoder gives historical background to songs, and makes introductions
    00:01:01 Marvin Wetzel performs "My Uncle" (in Pennsylvania German)
    00:03:42 Marvin Wetzel performs a song in Pennsylvania German
    00:04:55 Marvin Wetzel speaks (in Pennsylvania German)
    00:06:21 Ferris Herzog performs "The Laughing Song" (in English)
    00:07:47 Ferris Herzog performs "The ABC Song" (in Pennsylvania German)
    00:09:41 Mabel Snyder and Mary Dennehauer perform "Nun danket alle Gott" (Now Thank We All Our God); a hymn of thanksgiving, in Pennsylvania German]
    00:10:48 Mary Dennehauer speaks about being confirmed; church services (in English)
    00:11:39 Mabel Snyder speaks (in Pennsylvania German) about German church services she attended
    00:13:42 Don Yoder [?] provides an introduction to the interview, plus a segment on prayer (includes table prayers)
    00:14:00 Mabel Snyder sings "Seg ne diese schpise"
    00:14:28 Table prayer, spoken by Mabel Snyder
    00:15:29 Lord's Prayer (Pater Unser) (in Pennsylvania German), spoken by Mabel Snyder
    00:16:00 Lord's Prayer (Pater Unser) (in Pennsylvania German; in Pennsylvania German), spoken by Mary Dennehauer
    00:16:31 Reformed version of Lord's Prayer (Pater Unser; in Pennsylvania German), spoken by Paul Brumbach
    00:17:58 "Glava" (The Creed; in Pennsylvania German), spoken by Mabel Snyder
    00:19:07 Paul Brumbach recites a little child's prayer (in Pennsylvania German (cut off by problems with source audio)
    00:19:24 Mary Dennehauer recites a table prayer (in English)
    00:19:36 Paul Brumbach recites a prayer (in English)
    00:19:49 Mary or Mabel recites a prayer (in English)
    00:20:17 Mary or Mabel recites a prayer (in Pennsylvania German)
    00:21:17 Paul Brumbach recites a prayer (in Pennsylvania German)
    00:23:05 Mabel Snyder talks about harvest home celebration in German and Reformed Lutheran churches (spoken in Pennsylvania German)
  - Sound recording, August 30-31, 1961, RAA 46839; 1 sound tape reel (00:32:10): analog, 7 1/2 ips, half track, mono; 7 in. (Item-id AFC 2003/051: SR005)
    1st Pennsylvania Dutch Harvest Frolic.
    00:00:06 Don Yoder introduces Elmira Layton
    00:01:00 Elmira Layton talks about protective power of "himmel brefe" (letter from heaven) (in Pennsylvania German and English?)
    00:02:11 Elmira Layton talks about the candle used to heal her sister in a powwowing (in English)
    00:03:35 Elmira Layton tells the candle story (in Pennsylvania German)
    00:05:29 Mabel Snyder tells a story about her husband cured by a Catholic powwow (in English)
    00:12:30 Mabel Snyder tells a story about her husband cured by a Catholic powwow (highlights in Pennsylvania German)
    00:16:10 Introduction [Don Yoder?]; gives background on Sophia Eberley (niece of Sophia Bailer)
    00:16:53 Sophia Eberley speaks about powwowing (in Pennsylvania German and English)
  - Sound recording, July 1951, RAA 46840; 1 sound tape reel (Side A, part 1: 00:06:22, Side A, part 2: 00:32:41, Side A, complete: 00:32:41, Side B: 00:32:41): analog, 3 3/4 (Side A, part 1) and 7 1/2 ips (Side A, part 2, Side A complete, and Side B), mono; 7 in. (Item-id AFC 2003/051: SR006)
    2nd Annual Pennsylvania Dutch Folk Festival; Kutztown, Pennsylvania. Broadcast by WEEU radio. The singing group was from Lykens Valley, Valley View, Pennsylvania, and led by Rev. Harry Menser. Don Yoder is the announcer.
    Digitization notes: three splice points wore out during digitization. Points were reattached and the tape was transferred. The tape was recorded at two different speeds, and therefore had to be played back at two different speeds. The third file reflects the differing sections.
    Side A, part 1 (formerly identified as SR006a)
    00:00:01 unidentified man #1 leads hymn in Pennsylvania German
    00:00:39 Don Yoder [?] announces next two hymns
    00:00:56 the congregation sings "O Himmel O Himmel Wie Sies Be Schtu" (O Heaven O Heaven How Sweet You Are)
    00:02:43 the congregation sings "Yesus War Schoon Middons" (Jesus was With Us and He is Still With Us)
    00:04:02 an unidentified man introduces Jim Miller (his father-in-law)
    00:04:25 Jim Miller and the congregation sing "Ich Will Schafen" (on the theme of working out one's own salvation)
    0:05:47 Unidentified song performed by the congregation (original audio changes speed; the result is too fast)
    Side A, part 2 (was formerly identified as SR006c)
    00:00:01 a singing group performs an unidentified song (recording was started at a speed that was too fast, then was corrected)
    00:00:30 a singing group performs an unidentified song (same song as above; this may be a retake)
    00:03:34 Don Yoder gives a history of settlers who came 150 years ago; churches; spirituals in Pennsylvania German; introduces singing group from Lykens Valley, Valley View, Pennsylvania; they represent the United Brethren way of singing
    00:08:51 singing group performs "In the Wilderness" (begins in English, changes to Pennsylvania German and then back to English)
    00:10:07 singing group performs an unidentified song
    00:11:08 singing group performs an unidentified song ["Mir Wandren..."?]
    00:12:10 singing group performs "Ich wil schapen"
    00:13:17 singing group performs an unidentified song
    00:14:15 singing group performs "Wie lieblich...Yesus"
    00:15:06 Rev. Harry Menser speaks
    00:16:14 singing group performs an unidentified song
    00:17:33 singing group performs an unidentified song
    00:19:00 singing group performs an unidentified song
    00:19:49 singing group performs "O Himmel, O Himmel Wie Siese Bie Schtu" (in Pennsylvania German)
    00:21:01 singing group performs "Singet Hallelujah"
    00:22:05 Don Yoder introduces Peter Kirschner (Reading, Pennsylvania)
    00:22:34 Peter Kirschner performs "A Family Worship Him" (a bush meeting song)
    00:23:41 Peter Kirschner performs "O Hah Schtenkin Stig Nada" (O Lord, Send Us They Blessing) (to the tune of "Oh, Dear, What Can the Matter Be")
    00:25:20 Peter Kirschner performs "Yesus..." (Jesus Has Been With Us, and He is Still With Us, and He Says He Will Go With Us to the End)
    00:26:47 Peter Kirschner performs "Dropen in dem Scheinen Himmel" (in Pennsylvania German)
    00:28:20 singing group performs "Roll Jordan Roll" (in English)
    00:29:22 singing group performs "On the Resurrection Morning We Shall Rise"
    00:30:07 singing group performs an unidentified song
    00:30:43 singing group performs "Down in the Deep, Deep Sea"
    00:31:51 closing announcement by George Carroll
    2nd Annual Pennsylvania Dutch Folk Festival; Kutztown, Pennsylvania. Broadcast by WEEU radio. No log.
  - Sound recording, undated, RAA 46841; 1 sound tape reel (00:23:35): analog, 7 1/2 ips, half track, mono; 7 in. (Item-id AFC 2003/051: SR007)
    A female announcer introduces Bessie Ostroff. Bessie Ostroff, 67 years old, from Smila [SMEE-leh], Russia [now Ukraine]. She has been in the US for 50 years; no formal education in this country. She speaks about Jewish folk beliefs in regard to pregnancy, a woman's personal care, and the child, post-partum. She explains about the bris (ritual circumcision and naming), giving a child who is sick a second name, and other beliefs. Mr. Ostroff tells a story about his father hiring a gypsy to heal one of his children. Mrs. Ostroff speaks about death customs, including "sitting shiva."
  - Sound recording, July 2-3, 1962, RAA 46842; 1 sound tape reel (00:26:35): analog, 7 1/2 ips, half track, mono; 7 in. (Item-id AFC 2003/051: SR008)
    William Yeakel and John Moyer are the participants.
    00:00:01 Don Yoder announces this is a recording of Pennsylvania spirituals
    00:00:07 song in Pennsylvania German
    00:01:10 second song in Pennsylvania German
    00:02:05 "Praise the Lord O My Soul" (in English)
    00:04:38 one man performs a song in Pennsylvania German
    00:05:26 one man performs a song in Pennsylvania German (the same song as performed by unidentified man #1)
    00:06:08 one man performs a song in Pennsylvania German (same words as above but possibly a different tune)
    00:07:27 one man performs a song in Pennsylvania German
    00:08:05 one man performs a song in Pennsylvania German
    00:09:16 one man performs a song in Pennsylvania German
    00:10:27 one man performs a song in Pennsylvania German
    00:10:59 one man introduces the next hymn he will sing; he says he will sing it in German (Pennsylvania German?)
    00:11:33 one man performs a song in Pennsylvania German
    00:13:13 both men perform a song in Pennsylvania German
    00:14:00 both men perform a song in Pennsylvania German
    00:15:20 both men perform a song in Pennsylvania German
    00:16:17 both perform a song in Pennsylvania German
    00:17:15 both perform a song in Pennsylvania German
    00:18:29 John introduces the next hymn he will sing
    00:18:55 John performs "Ich wille im in bleiben trie" [?] (in Pennsylvania German)
    00:19:48 William [who has a more robust voice] performs "Ich wille im in bleiben trie" [?] (in Pennsylvania German)
    00:20:35 William [?] performs a song in Pennsylvania German
    00:21:17 both perform "In de Rue" [?] (in Pennsylvania German)
    00:22:01 both perform "Komme to Yesu" [?] in Pennsylvania German
    00:23:33 William [?] introduces the song "O Come to Hiram Yegel" [?]
  - Sound recording, 1938-1960, RAA 46843; 1 sound tape reel (Side A: 00:30:45, Side B: 00:25:46): analog, 7 1/2 ips, half track, mono; 7 in. (Item-id AFC 2003/051: SR009)
    SR009 appears to have originally been recorded only in the first track. However, an echo/print-through signal is present on the second track. Details draw on accompanying documentation. John A. Hostetler sent this tape to Don Yoder.
    Sung by Joni Easch and Eli J. Bontrager. Recorded by Alan Lomax, April 13, 1938. See the field notes in Alan Lomax Ohio and Indiana collection (AFC 1938/004) for further details. Hostetler cites page 748 in the Ausband as the source of the hymn on AFS 01766 A; Lomax cites page 738.
    00:00:08 Gross sind die Werke des Herrn (AFS 01763 A1)
    00:2:17 Herzlich tut mich erfreuen (AFS 01763 A2)
    00:04:29 Herzlich tut mich erfreuen (AFS 01763 B1; conclusion)
    00:06:08 Muss es nun Sein gescheiden (AFS 01763 B2)
    00:08:46 O Gott Vater, wir Loben Dich (AFS 01764 A)
    00:13:05 Der Winter kalt, rauh, engestalt (AFS 01764 B)
    00:17:53 Lebt Friedsam (AFS 01765 A)
    00:20:17 Wann der Herr die G'fangnisz Zion (AFS 01765 B)
    00:23:24 Wo kommt das her, O Jesu Christ (AFS 01766 A)
    00:26:08 Merkt auf mit Fleisz, ein Himmelspeis (AFS 01766 B)
    "So will ichs aber heben an" is from Lomax's collection. The next five are from the Marcus Bach "Preserving Iowa's Religious Heritage" collection, part 1 (AFC 1943/013), recorded February 8, 1943; see notes for SR011 below. They were performed by "Hay" John Miller, his wife, and others, near Kalona, Iowa. The final four selections are recordings of Samuel H. Peachey and his wife Julia, in Belleville, Pennsylvania. They were recorded by Hostetler on July 10, 1960. See notes for SR095.
    00:00:24 So will ichs aber heben an (AFS 01767 A)
    00:03:46 O Gott Vater (AFS 06994 A)
    00:06:57 Gelobt sei Gott (AFS 06994 B)
    00:09:55 Wachet auf (AFS 06995 A1)
    00:12:23 Es sind Zween weg (AFS 06995 A2)
    00:13:36 Lebt Friedsam Sprach Christus (AFS 06995 B)
    00:16:26 Lebt Friedsam Sprach Christus [Samuel Peachey, lead vocal]
    00:21:06 Muss es nun sein gescheiden
    00:24:46 Tisch Gebet, Fünf Tausand Menschen
  - Sound recording, April 19, 1968, RAA 46844; 1 sound tape reel (Side A, part 1: 01:54:34, Side A, part 2: 00:22:19): analog, 1 7/8 ips, half track, mono; 7 in. (Item-id AFC 2003/051: SR010)
    Hutterite baptismal service, recorded by John A. Hostetler. See the tape box image for details. This tape is a copy made for Yoder by Hostetler.
    Digitization notes: The source tape had issues with speed fluctuation. The digital file for Side A was divided into two files to compensate for the WAV file size limitations (when the tape was digitized in 2005). Part 2 audio ends at 00:22:13. Part 1 was formerly named SR010_1, and Part 2 was formerly named SR010_2.
  - Sound recording, February 1943, RAA 46845; 1 sound tape reel (00:02:37): analog, 7 1/2 ips, full track, mono; 5 in. (Item-id AFC 2003/051: SR011)
    Copy of AFS 06995B. Recorded in Ames, Iowa, by Marcus Bach and Addison Alspach. Sung by twelve Old Order Amish men and women living in the Kalona, Iowa, farming area some 10 miles from the University of Iowa. They came to the campus to record several of their Altdeutsche Lieder. A man leads the group in singing "Lebt friedsam, sprach Christus."
  - Sound recording, undated, RAA 46846; 1 sound tape reel (01:36:28): analog, 3 3/4 ips, half track, mono; 7 in. (Item-id AFC 2003/051: SR012)
    The tape was made by Peter F. Edelman and Alan Solar for Yoder's Religious Theology 523 class. See SR150 for another recording made by them.